Finding Aid for Carlisle Family papers, 1860-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carlisle Family papers 1860-1972
Carlisle family.
1.5 linear foot
851593 Aa 2
Daniel Carlisle family of Buchanan, Michigan; family correspondence, diaries, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Daniel Carlisle (donor no. 3696 ) and came to the library in 1960.
The collection is open to research.
The Daniel Carlisle family were residents of Buchanan, Michigan. Hannah L. Carlisle (born April 22, 1823, died Feb. 17, 1906) served as a nurse during the Civil War and was stationed mainly in Kentucky. In 1866 she taught school in Columbus, Kentucky for the American Freedmen's Aid Commission. Her husband, Daniel Carlisle (born Sept. 22, 1797, died March 31, 1872) then in his sixties and in poor health remained at the family home in Buchanan.
The Carlisle family collection consists of two feet of material dating from 1860 to 1972. The papers relate to various members of the Daniel Carlisle family of Buchanan, Michigan. The collection contains correspondence between Hannah L. Carlisle and her husband, Daniel Carlisle. Include as well are letters and eight of Hannah Carlisle's diaries, written between 1885 and 1900 and largely concerning her life in Dead wood, South Dakota.
Other family members represented in the collection are William and Phyllis Carlisle and Vivian Carlisle. The letters of William D. Carlisle concern his service in the US Navy during World War II. The letters of Phyllis Carlisle relate both to her student life at the University of Michigan during the early 1940s and to her service in the Waves during the war. The letters of Vivian Carlisle were written while a student at the University of Michigan and Michigan State University during the 1940s.
Other items of interest is a folder of genealogical material and a letter written by Francis A. Carlisle while serving in Cuba during the Spanish-American War, describing his experiences.
Subjects:
Allegan County (Mich.); American Freedmen's Aid Commission.; Branch County (Mich.); Buchanan (Mich.); Burr Oak (Mich.); Carlisle family.; Cuba.; Deadwood (S.D.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Buchanan Lodge No. 75 (Buchanan, Mich.); Kentucky.; Little Prairie Ronde (Mich.); Methodist Episcopal Church. Niles District (Mich.); Nurses--Kentucky.; South Dakota.; South Dakota--Social life and customs.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Teachers--Kentucky.; United States--Armed Forces--Women.; United States. Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States Sanitary Commission.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Women--Kentucky.; Women--South Dakota.; Women teachers--Kentucky.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Carlisle, Daniel, 1797-1872.; Carlisle, Hannah, 1823-1906.
Contributors:
Carlisle, Daniel, 1797-1872.; Carlisle, Francis A.; Carlisle, Hannah, 1823-1906.; Carlisle, Phyllis.; Carlisle, William.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - Genealogical Information compiled by various members of the Carlisle family. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - circa 1850-1899 (Box 1)
    - circa 1900-1940, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Undated post-1940, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1862 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1863 (Box 1)
    - July 1863-December 1864 (Box 1)
    - 1865 (Box 1)
    - 1866 (Box 1)
    - 1867-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870-1874 (Box 1)
    - 1875-1876 (Box 1)
      (include program of a camp meeting of the Niles district of the Michigan Conference of the Methodist Church, August 15, 1876)
    - 1877-1879 (Box 1)
      (include letters from Little Prairie Ronde, 1877)
    - 1880 (Box 1)
      (include letters written from Ganges)
    - 1881 (Box 1)
    - 1882-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 1)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 1)
    - 1889 (Box 1)
    - 1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1893 (Box 1)
    - 1894 (Box 1)
    - 1895 (Box 1)
    - 1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897 (Box 1)
    - 1898 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1899 (Box 1)
    - April-December 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1902 (Box 1)
    - April-December 1902 (Box 1)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 1)
    - 1905 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1906 (Box 1)
    - April-December 1906 (Box 1)
    - 1907 (Box 1)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1912 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 1)
    - 1915 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
      (include letter April 6, 1917 of Daniel Carlisle II written from a Texas army camp where he was stationed during World War I)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1922 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - 1925, 1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1939 (Box 1)
    - January-May 1940 (Box 1)
    - June-July 1940 (Box 1)
    - August-October 1940 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1940 (Box 1)
    - January 1941 (Box 1)
    - February-December 1941 (Box 1)
    - January-August 1942 (Box 1)
    - September 1942 (Box 1)
    - October 1942 (Box 1)
    - November 1942, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - December 1942 (Box 1)
    - January 1943 (Box 1)
    - February 1943 (Box 1)
    - May. 1943 (Box 1)
    - June 1943 (Box 1)
    - July 1943 (Box 1)
    - August 1943 (Box 1)
    - September 1943 (Box 1)
    - October-November 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - January 1945 (Box 1)
    - February 1945 (Box 1)
    - March 1945 (Box 1)
    - April 1945 (Box 1)
    - May-June 1945 (Box 1)
    - July-August 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1972 (Box 1)
  - Letters circa 1940-1945, of William D. Carlisle concerning Navy Service, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters circa 1940, of Phyllis Carlisle while a student at the University of Michigan, and a Wave during World War II (Box 2)
  - Letters circa 1943-1946, of Vivian Carlisle while a student at The University of Michigan, Michigan State University, and a housewife following her marriage to David LaValle when she dropped out of school, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Diaries of Hannah Carlisle, 1889-1891, 1893-1895, 1897, 1899 (fragment), and 1900, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)